Guide to the Herbert L. Packer Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Herbert L. Packer papers
1942-1972
SC0819
Packer, Herbert L., 1925-1972.
7 Linear feet (15 boxes)
The papers primarily contain correspondence, but also include articles, drafts, conference materials, financial records, and administrative files. Subjects include Packer's academic career at Yale and Stanford; his research and writing on the Alger Hiss trial; the government witness project undertaken at Stanford; and other legal issues. Correspondents include Robert Barnard, Edward N. Benjamin, Palmer L. Bevis, Warren Christopher, Robert A. Koch, Richard W. Lyman, Phil C. Neal, Louis B. Schwartz, Thomas W. Swan, Donald F. Turner and Edwin Zimmerman.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Correspondence in box 15 is restricted. The collection is otherwise open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Herbert L. Packer earned his B.A. (1944) and LL.B. (1949) at Yale University. After private practice in a Washington law firm, he came to Stanford as Associate Professor of Law in 1956 and was appointed Professor in 1959. From 1967 to 1969 he served as Vice Provost for Academic Planning and Programs. After suffering a massive stroke, he returned to the Law School in the fall of 1969. He was named Jackson Eli Reynolds Professor of Law in 1971. Packer's first book, EX-COMMUNIST WITNESSES: FOUR STUDIES IN FACT FINDING, was conceived at the time he came to Stanford and was supported by a research grant from the Fund for the Republic.
Description of the Collection
The papers primarily contain correspondence, but also include articles, drafts, conference materials, financial records, and administrative files. Subjects include his academic career at Yale and Stanford; his research and writing on the Alger Hiss trial; the government witness project undertaken at Stanford; and other legal issues. Correspondents include Robert Barnard, Edward N. Benjamin, Palmer L. Bevis, Warren Christopher, Robert A. Koch, Richard W. Lyman, Phil C. Neal, Louis B. Schwartz, Thomas W. Swan, Donald F. Turner and Edwin Zimmerman.
Access Terms
Barnard, Robert.; Benjamin, Edward N.; Bevis, Palmer L.; Christopher, Warren.; Koch, Robert A.; Lyman, Richard W., 1923-2012.; Neal, Phil C.; Packer, Herbert L., 1925-1972.; Schwartz, Louis B.; Stanford University. School of Law--Faculty.; Swan, Thomas W.; Turner, Donald F.; Zimmerman, Edwin M.; Communism--United States; Governmental investigations--United States; Law--Study and teaching--United States
Collection Contents
- Chronological file, outgoing, Aug.-Oct. 1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Nov. 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Chronological file, outgoing, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Chronological file, outgoing, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Chronological file, outgoing, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Jan.-Aug. 1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Sept.-Dec. 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Chronological file, outgoing, 1960 Jan.-June (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Chronological file, outgoing, 1960 July-Dec. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Jan.-Feb. 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Chronological file, outgoing, March-April 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Chronological file, outgoing, May-June 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Chronological file, outgoing [includes part of an application for a Faculty Fellowship and the Report of the Special Adivsory Committee on Credential Revocation Procedures to the State Board of Education], July-Aug. 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Sept. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Chronological file, outgoing [includes his paper "The Warren Commission Report"], October 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Chronological file, outgoing, November 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Dec. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Chronological file, outgoing: Curriculum Committee, Dec. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Jan.-April 1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Chronological file, outgoing, May-July 1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Chronological file, outgoing, July-Oct. 20 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Oct. 21-Dec. 17, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Jan. 5-March 18, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Chronological file, outgoing, March 21-April 28, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Chronological file, outgoing, May 2-June 24, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Chronological file, outgoing, June 27-Sept. 26, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Oct. 3-Dec. 2, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Dec. 5, 1966-Jan. 1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Chronological file, outgoing, April 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Chronological file, outgoing, May-June 1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Chronological file, outgoing, July-Aug. 16. 1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Aug. 19-Sept. 1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Chronological file, outgoing, October 1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Nov.-Dec. 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Jan.-Feb. 12, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Feb. 13-Mar. 12, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Chronological file, outgoing, April-July 1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Chronological file, outgoing, August-Sept. 1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Chronological file, outgoing [includes list], Oct.-Nov. 15, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Chronological file, outgoing [includes list], Nov. 16-Dec. 1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Chronological file, outgoing [includes list], Jan. 1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Chronological file, outgoing, [includes partial list], February 1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Chronological file, outgoing, March 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Chronological file, outgoing, April 1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Chronological file, outgoing, May-June 1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Chronological file, outgoing, July-Aug. 1970 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Sept. 1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Oct.-Nov. 13, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Nov. 17-Dec. 1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Jan.-Feb. 1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Mar.-May 1971 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Chronological file, outgoing, June-Oct. 1971 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Nov.-Dec. 1971 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Chronological file, outgoing, January 1972 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Chronological file, outgoing, Feb.-March 1972 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Chronological file, outgoing, April-May 1972 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Chronological file, outgoing, June 1972 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Chronological file, outgoing, July 1972 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1948-49 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1952-53 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1957-58 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1959-62 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, general A-F, 1959-60 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, general G-L, 1958-60 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, general M-Q, 1958-60 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, general R-S, 1958-60 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, general T-Z, 1957-60 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, Jan.-June 1969 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, Aug.-Dec. 1969 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, Jan.-May 1970 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, June-Dec. 1970 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Jan.-Feb. 1971 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, March-Dec. 1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Personal correspondence A-D, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Personal correspondence E-K, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Personal correspondence L-P, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Personal correspondence R-Z, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- 9th Circuit Judicial Conference Correspondence, (with note by Nancy Packer concerning accomodations), 1958 and 2003 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- AALS [Assoc. of American Law Schools] Committee on Teaching Law in the Liberal Arts Curriculum, Correspondence re, 1957-58 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- AALS Criminal Law Round Table, Correspondence re, 1957-59 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Academic correspondence, April-Dec. 1957 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Academic correspondence, Jan. 1956-March 1957 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- ACLU, Correspondence, 1958-59 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Appointment (Vice Provost for Academic Planning), congratulatory correspondence, 1966-67 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Arson Study Correspondence re, 1959-60 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Barnard, Robert, Correspondence re testimony of Barnard and his sister to G.S.A., 1959 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Change magazine, text of article and correspondence, 1970-71 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Christopher, Warren, correspondence, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Christopher, Warren, correspondence, 1953-72 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Clippings and press releases (personal), 1968-69 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Coif Award (for his book THE LIMITS OF THE CRIMINAL SACTION), correspondence re, 1970-71 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Conference of Chief Justices (S.F.), correspondence re talk for, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Conference on the control of narcotics addiction, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Conference on the control of narcotics addiction, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Consitutional immunities and privileges, correspondence and text for chapter on, 1960-63 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Crime Tariff, The, text and correspondence re, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Criminal Procedure: course outline, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Encyclopaedia Briannica, correspondence and text of entry for, 1959-60 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Faculty committee for Government Witness Project, correspondence, 1955-56 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- W. H. Ferry / J. R. McDonough correspondence re Government Witness study, 1959-60 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Ford Foundation fellowship [for study on criminal policy in a free society], correspondence and other records, 1958-62 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Foundations - applications, etc., 1966 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Guggenheim Award, 1970-72 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Law and Medical Schools, correspondence re joint program between, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Lawyers Committee for Civil Rights Under Law, correspondence, 1963-64 (Box 10, Folder 13)
- NAACP, correspondence, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Neal, Phil C., correspondence, 1952-58 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Packer, "The Courts, The Police and the Rest of Us," text of an address at Northwestern, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Packer, "Great Britan and the Near Eastern Crisis of 1878," in competition for the Andrew D. White Freshman Prize, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Packer, 3 papers for the Joint Committee for the Revision of the Penal Code, CA Legislature, 1965-66 (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Packer and Lloyd Cutler, article for Harper's, text and correspondence, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Packer, Nancy, letters to Herb, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Personal - Book Of the Month Club: catalogs and resignation letter, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Personal finance - salary, 1970-72 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Personal finance, 1969-72 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Publications, correspondence re, 1957-58 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Publications, correspondence re, 1960-61 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Publications, correspondence re, 1961-62 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Publications, correspondence re, 1962-63 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Publications, correspondence re, 1963-64 (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Publications, correspondence re, 1964-65 (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Publications, correspondence re, 1965-66 (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Review of Handler's Antitrust in Perspective, correspondence re, 1957-58 (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Review of Warren Commission, correspondence re, 1964-65 (Box 11, Folder 14)
- Reviews, correspondence re, 1965-66 (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Reynolds Chair appointment, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Sabbatical [1963-64], 1962-64 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Sabina Hart Connolly Prize and Cragin Award (Hillhouse High School), correspondence re, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Schwartz, Louis B. (U. of Penn.), correspondence re therapeutic abortion research and various writing projects, 1958-60 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Stanford, correspondence and miscellany, 1955-60 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Stanford [correspondence, statements, etc. re political and administrative issues], 1970-71 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Stanford [correspondence, statements, etc. re political and administrative issues], 1971-72 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Stanford, Board of Trustees, 1967-69 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Stanford position not taken, correspondence re, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Study of Witnesses File I, correspondence, clippings, 1954-56 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Study of Witnesses File II, correspondence, statements, and other material, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Study of Witnesses File III, correspondence, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Study of Witnesses File IV, correspondence, press coverage, and copy of "Tale of Two Typewriters,", 1958 (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Study of Witnesses File V, correspondence and press coverage, 1955-56 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Study of Witnesses File VI, correspondence re Fund for the Republic, 1955-58 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Study of Witnesses VII Confidential, correspondence, 1956-60 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Study of Witnesses VIII formal documentation, 1955 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Study of Witnesses, Index to files I - VIII (Box 13, Folder 5)
- [Study of witnesses] Government Witness Project, table of contents and index of testimony (Box 13, Folder 6)
- [Study of witnesses] Project, correspondence and memorandum, 1955 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- [Study of witnesses] Project, correspondence, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- [Study of witnesses] Project, correspondence, 1957-58 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- "A Tale of Two Typewriters" (pre-publication), correspondence re, 1957-58 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- "A Tale of Two Typewriters" correspondence re, 1958-59 (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Travel, 1970-72 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Yale Law School, correspondence, 1969-72 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Yale Moot Court of Appeals 1947 Spring Term. Brief by Packer (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Yale: The Adamson Case: a study in constitutional technique, honors paper, 1948 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Yale: assorted class papers, 1945 and undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Yale: The Image in the Mirror, The Yale Law Journal, September 1947 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Yale: paper on negtionable instruments, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Yale: "Selections from Cicero's Pro M. Caelio to Illustrate the Life and Times of Catullus" [mimeographed paper, intro in English, rest in Latin], undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Yale: short story manuscript, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Yarmolinsky, Adam - testimony re investigation of government witnesses, along with text of Eric Sevareid radio broadcast on loyalty, November 1955 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Zimmerman, Edwin, correspondence, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Letters of recommendation, 1960-61 (Box 15)
- Dean of Law School Search Committee correspondence, 1962-63 (Box 15)
- Restricted letters pulled from other folders, 1972 (Box 15)